To go right up the border and stay in my own time zone. That's a
whole lot easier. And so what I will also
make fun of as I'm working with a beginner is drawing
this line. Now, Belarus is just on
the other side also, but they decided not to change their clocks.
And so sometimes it is 1 hour here
difference, but sometimes here is 2 hours
difference because they stay on the same clock.
So not only am I walking from Poland to Belarus,
but I am now gaining 2 hours of life back
or losing 2 hours of life by just simply moving 1.
So that means that they invented two
different time zones in the same area. And so when
I sing up in this area,
I can be in that mode. Or La.
Or La. I have all these options
up in here. But my question to a beginner is
what do the animals care?
There are animals that cross these borders all the time.
Will a fox reset his watch when he
crosses over? Does a bird flying this way or that way change
his meal plan? Will the snakes
care that they're in Belarus versus Poland? The idea
here is simple, that there is natural forces.
Time moves. The earth is revolving. All that's true.
But humans have set down borders, a lot
of borders, and we socially agree to those borders.
And so, yes, there are different resonant zones
that happen inside us as we sing,
but we create the boundary between them by
creating a group of pitches because that's what brains like.
They want things to be boundaried. And so this EF here
doesn't mention one thing every time when I
was in college and they would tell me that that's where the first passagio is
for male, I would say, at what volume?
Because it matters. And so the idea of
thinking of all this multicolor or multidimensional
sound is that we have lots of options.
And so I tend to ask one or
two questions are you comfortable? Are you in
control? So when somebody is singing La La,
I don't even have to ask if they're comfortable. I know they're not.
And I don't usually ask if they're in control,
but it depends what style of music they like, because sometimes a
very raspy or distorted sound is their intention,
is their desired outcome. So I ask them, is that a
sound you mean to make? And if they say yes,
yeah, that's the sound they mean to make. Then I ask them,
are you comfortable making that sound? And I then
move on from there. So I let them decide,
and I think that's very important. But what I tell about this
resonant package wait a minute. Let me get my hand right. This resonant package,
all right, here is that for animals, this is
shared space. So I
want people to think of resonance as wildlife.
Resonance will roam where it wants to.
So beginners will often feel a little insecure if
they feel as
they sing higher or lower, they may sense the resonance
in their body and of course then they may sense it wanting to go
up into their head. And if they block that because they
feel that's out of control. I will remind them that
the wildlife is going across these borders
here very freely. It roams where it
wants to, where the food is. And so we
want to think of resonance as a shared space.
There are no boundaries in the body. And this shared
space to me is the whole message of mixed voice,
is to keep blending and keep combining and to
allow all of this area here to be a shared space and that
it is percentages. We may be dominant in one
area and
then dominant in another area, but there is no border,
there is no line. And any which
way you can get a beginner singer to change
their perception that there is rigid boundaries,
that's a good thing. And so I have many analogies,
but I decided on this one because I wanted to try out my
little map of Poland. And so the idea of
whatever a person's advocation is,
what their job is, I will try to discover what information
they already have. You could also use temperature.
There is obviously a big swing in temperature. From zero Celsius
to 100 Celsius is a wide swing.
But where's warm begin? Where does cold
begin? So everybody has a personal
thing that they will say they're cold or warm,
but it won't be the same degree for everyone.
And so that idea of a spectrum is a
very important one. For a beginner to begin to plant
the seed, they will need coordination, they will
need skill to be able to navigate around their bias.
And that's all it is, is a prejudice, a bias,
and it's based on a fear of embarrassment. And so
they do not want to venture from land to
land. It's much easier for them to stay in one place
or another. And so I encourage them to cross
the borders, to think of this like wildlife as a free space,
as it's very important for them to be able to navigate.
So I say share the space. And I'm always saying
this because I want them to share the space in order to
free their voice. So it's easy to travel.
Often a beginner will come back to me and say it can't
be that easy. Yeah, you say that because you can sing through that
area is what they'll tell me. And I'll say, no, you could
do it if you ask for the sound and explore sounds as
play, because that's exactly what you did when you asked
for a sound when you were this years old.
So if it seems like something very difficult to them,
it's because they're not remembering that when they really championed
this thing called voice use. They were one year old,
and if they can do it when they were one, how complex the
speech is of any language. I often
ask them to Google, is it singing
in the MRI? I think that's the name of the video.
And there's also X ray videos of people speaking.
And they're marvelous to show, to beginners.
Because the complexity of what's going on
inside us while we sing is a miracle.
But it's also innate meaning. The person
that's being X rayed at that moment is not thinking about the tongue
and the palate and the air and the tube above it.
They're simply thinking about a communication. So they are asking for
that communication to come through. That's what we did
when we were little tots that's how we learned to use our voice.
And we have our parents to thank for that, what they gave us.
But it is that simple premise that I like to begin
with, with a person that identifies as a beginner.
And so now if there's any questions, I'll be happy to
entertain them.
I'm watching the chat and there are no questions
so far. Oh, yes, there are.
There's people that are not asking them.
Show of hands, how many people think of pitch and
tone and volume and time as the same
thing all combined as one.
And so the idea of separating it and this is
how we're taught it's not our fault. We are taught pitch is frequency,
volume is amplitude, right? And we see these pictures
of them separated and we hear about these things and
we look at even Voice vista or whatever that program is called,
and we see how things are separated, like so.
But it's often not discussed as a single
sound. And that's exactly what singers
are looking to cultivate, is the package, the entirety
of it, because the empathy of
a listener is at stake. What we're really looking
to do is to create a message. And the way we create
those messages is with sounds. And so the sound
if I were to say this, I've never
been so happy in my life. This is the best day.
I can't believe how good today is going.
That doesn't sound very believable. Oh, my God, I am so
depressed. I have never been so incredibly depressed in my
life. I think I'm just going to kill myself right now.
That's not appropriate. And so if we are singing
and now hijacked by the strict
muscle rules we have so
if I sing I love you that
way, it may not convey what I
love you conveys.
There's a little mystery if I delay and there's
that element of time, very important element of time.
Or if I love you or
I love you or
I love you or I love
you that doesn't sound very good.
Or I love you that's a little
creepy. Or I love you.
I love you. So there's many ways,
a million ways to sing the same three words.
Some will hit the heart, some will hit the head,
some will go right over because they're not appropriate.
So we as singers and teachers of singers
need to be addressing the whole of the sound
because it is the whole of the sound that is being assessed by the
listener. And so if somebody is
struggling with pitch, often I will focus on their timbre
or their volume and I will tell them that we're working
on those and they will say, no, I'm always
sharp or I'm always flat. And they need to work on that specifically.
And I will inform them, you're always flat or sharp
because your volume or your timbre or your timing
is inappropriate because it's out of
control. Again, we go to those two factors, comfort and
control. And so I will inform them after
a while, they start to get the image that one affects
the other. And so the idea of putting them
all together to make it holistic in terms of sound,
I think is a more accurate approach, is more beneficial
to the end result people are looking for.
And so is there any questions now about separating these into
four variables?
Maybe I will ask the question, as we know,
hundreds of exercises for a
problem. So there is a vowel
exercise which will help you with timbre.
There is an exercise to CTTA muscles coordination
that works on pitch. And I
heard your exercises before and I just loved how
they join all those different ideas.
How do you construct the exercise? How do you think about it
to do more than one thing at once? Because all
the exercises you already mentioned are also doing everything at once.
It is simply a label that you're putting on it.
And so in other words, when you're saying
to a student, okay, now we're going to work the CT muscle.
And we'll do there
is a specific volume I am singing at, there's a specific timbre
I am creating. And it is under the illusion
that I'm just isolating one muscle, which is also impossible.
And so anytime we're trying to work just one muscle
within the vocal mechanism, other muscles are always
being introduced, of course. And so the CT
never acts alone without the thyroid arynoid.
Those arynoids in the back are also very active.
And so it's a focus that we're
moving. And so the idea here is that I'm just always explaining
to people I'm working with that it's a sound,
it's not just a pitch. And so the idea of keeping
that made me extend, how can I keep
that presence? How can I keep that premise
alive? And so as I'm inventing exercises,
because I have somebody that's stubborn in front of me, let's say I will
keep asking myself I have to analyze physically
what they're doing. Of course, that's what we do as teachers. And then I have
to say to myself, okay, but you can't feel the CT
muscle, you can't feel the thyroid or retinoid muscle. So if I start mentioning that
to the student, they're going to go looking for something that feels
different than what they've been doing before. So I found that
tends to promote extraneous tensions, because now if
no, I want you to use your CT muscle, we're going to pull the folds
a little more to get that pitch in tune. They're going to add
in muscles they can feel as a feedback loop,
and it will give them a difference. I was doing
this. Now I feel different and I hit the pitch.
That's a problem. When we get success that included
extra muscle because now the brain is going to say, AHA.
So I want to feel these muscles lock in.
That's how I learned because I was singing for
a living first and then learned
about the voice second. And so when you sing for a living,
you have to make it through the song. You have to make it through the
night, you have to make it through the week, or else you don't eat,
you don't pay your rent, and you got to call your parents,
and they don't like that. And so the point here is that I
used pressure.