And so physically they will manifest.
They want to be physically comfortable
of course. But right now for beginners I think their emotions
are more important than the physical
stuff that I could get into them with muscle
tension and things like this I think it's a little premature.
And so I like to think of lessons same thing here
with control. I want to keep their control of
emotions to be what we're focusing on as
we work through some exercises and be playful with our voices.
And so I try to explain to them that lessons
in the beginning are a playground. They're a place
to explore. It's not a place of rules,
it's not a place of failure. You can't go wrong when you're in
the playground. It's all about tapping into your imagination
and seeing things as possibilities.
And so we just play with sounds and as easy
as that sounds there's a lot to it. And so I
think that exercises like I was saying before vocalizing
are much better to be playful with songs than songs.
Songs have too easy of a way to be
compared to of course the original artist but
also anyone else that we've heard sing the song.
And so it becomes an instant gap. When a beginner
sings a song they have the original in their mind and
they know they're coming short of it. And so this distance between
becomes their failure and will then hijack their
body because they know they're not meeting the standard that they
imagined. And I think that's unfair to
present that to a beginner singer that's just exploring.
And so I like to keep my beginner
singers singing exercises for probably longer than
they would like to because they're all interested in singing songs
and the songs they're interested in singing usually are the hardest ones
that they can possibly imagine. And so they're setting themselves up
for these little failures that I'm trying to help them avoid.
And so I will take a list of the songs they're
interested in and I will ask them what is it they like
about those songs? And I will then go and listen
to those songs to make sure that I'm hitting the same range that
they will need, that I'm creating the same physical instrument
that they will need. But I don't use the song to explore that
because I don't want them to have a memory of failing to
sing the song that they will take with them for
a very long time. And so the more headway,
the more time I can
get to spend with somebody just singing exercises the
better instrument I can prepare for them. So when they do approach the
songs they're better equipped that
the instrument can handle the elasticity that they're going
to ask for, the muscle independence that they're going to ask for.
And so with playing with sounds there are four
variables and these variables in sound are quite
important. First, one of course, get out of
the way. Here is pitch. Everybody's very concerned
about pitch. It's the one variable in
a sound where a layperson can understand
that we missed the target. And so everybody
tends to be very focused on pitch because
it will expose us in the beginning.
And therefore pitch, I feel, gets too much of the spotlight
because it is always going to be influenced by other things.
For instance, volume. If we bring
the volume down in somebody's voice,
it may be much easier for them to sing higher.
But if they're using volume
in order to get pitch, those two become one
and they are no longer independent. So obviously we see
this a lot with beginners or
they get louder as they sing higher. So they are
attaching volume and pitch as one. And so therefore,
I know when they head into a song they
will struggle to express themselves because every high note
will get louder and every low note will get softer.
And so it becomes very predictable to the listener.
And immediately we can understand this person
is not emoting right now. They're singing these
pitches, but they're not presenting the sentiment,
they're not feeling it. And so that brings us to that third
variable, which is timbre. And this is
very important because it's a big term.
Timbre has many subcategories to
it. Of course, it's the quality of a voice, but it's also
the onset, it's also the offset,
how we sustain the note, whether it has
vibrato or not. The overall quality, being nasal,
oral, breathy, pressed or clear,
all the many attributes. And timbre is very
important to a listener. So I think it should be upped
on the list to a beginner or someone with less experience
simply because the timbre is what speaks to the listener.
It's what gives them a lot of information about
the sentiment of the song. So when I hear a song
in Polish or when I hear a song in
Japanese or in Chinese, I can still understand
the sentiment because timbres of emotions
are universal. Sadness sounds the same all
around the planet. Happiness sounds the same.
Love sounds the same. Anguish sounds the same.
And so we spice, we add flavor to
our singing by looking at these individual
variables of a voice the pitch
of it, the volume of it and the timbre of it.
But another element, there are four that I think is often
forgotten, is time.
The duration of a note cannot be separated
from the other factors. So if somebody is holding
a note, holding a pitch for
a given amount of time and as they start to run longer,
3 seconds, 4 seconds, the note begins to
vary,
starts to go flat because their breathing is starting to squeeze their body
time becomes a very important element that they maintain the
same pitch within a given amount of time.
So many times I will hear a beginner
or new singer who's looking for exercises,
sing a scale and
they will just simply hold this note for as long as they have air left.
And so they've never decided what is the length
of that last pitch. They simply use how much air they have
left in their lungs to determine that.
And so this is a problem because it means they're training themselves
to always use all their air all the time.
And so I've devised some exercises to stop people doing that.
But I think it's important that we view these four
variables as independent, yet very dependent.
They all influence each other. And the best way I
can explain that, if you could see this,
I have some put this in front of me. I have some playdoh here.
And so if I take this playdoh, this is pink.
And if I take out a ball of it now
if I say to a student,
let's call this pink play, DOH pitch and
we can play with it,
I can stretch it, I can break it, I can make it thicker,
but it's not acting alone. Now I'll take some green playdoh
and if I take a lump of it, let's call this
volume oops right in front. So we have volume and pitch,
but they don't act independently.
I'm going to mesh them together because we cannot separate
this in nature. We have of course,
volume, which is the amplitude of a sound wave. And then
we have pitch, which is the number of frequencies or
number of wiggles per second vibrations. So then I will
use a yellow playdoh and say this is timbre.
A timbre does not act alone. So again,
we have to mish it into this ball that I'm
calling a sound. So now I have
timbre and volume and pitch all in this single
ball, which we call a sound.
But we're not done. We have still time to deal with.
So if I take a little bit of time,
this would be a short note and add that
in. But if I take a longer bit of time,
use this blue playdoh.
And now I'm combining time and volume and
pitch together and I'm
rolling it up and I'm playing yee or
a little chop.
So it is this process that I
ask vocal scientists often.
Here is a sound it has got in within it
pitch, volume, timbre and time.
How can we talk about one aspect?
So if I try to take a little piece of this, I want just
the what did I say pink? Pink was pitch.
So if I'm trying to isolate just pitch,
it's a fantasy for me to say to a student,
okay, we're going to work on your pitch because I cannot
take just the pink back out of this sound
without also volume coming with it and timbre coming
with it and time coming with it. So we
are always working with all four elements.
It's nice to talk about just pitch, it's nice to talk about
just volume or timbre. Like people love to
talk about belting or mix or heavy mix and have many
terms for these timbres. But it can never be separated from the
sound in reality. And so, especially for
beginners, I like to keep them in reality and speak of the whole
sound all the time. It is multicolored
because it's multidimensional. There's a
lot going into this. And I want the beginner perspective
to start to expand so they see things in
these dimensions. The sound I'm making has a pitch,
it also has a volume, also has a quality,
and it has a duration. And what that does by
talking about it is start to expand the way they
think about it. And that's really important that
I express that they can ask for a sound,
anything rather than a behavior. It's when we
isolate those four elements and start talking about
just pitch or just volume, and especially talking about
the behaviors that create it, we are also giving
them, I want to say,
a fantasy that those elements can be
separated. And so the sound they're asking for is
always all for going with them all the time.
And this really gets confusing for beginners
because there is so much talk about registers
and they know those behaviors to be real because
they can suffer from them.
And that's all the evidence they need. That's a thing they read
about online called Chest Voice and
Head Voice and Mix and everything
else, fry and whistle. They know these things exist because
they suffer from them. And so I try to again make
this holistic approach to be very friendly for them.
And so I will start, hopefully you can see this.
This is a landscape picture on
one side. Let me draw a line here. I hope
you can see it on get my finger here.
Right here is Poland and right here is
Lithuania. And down here is
Belarus. Wait, let me go this way. It's hard. I have new
respect for weather people that do this stuff. This is really
hard. And so wait right there. Now my
fingers on Belarus. So the point here is that
it is always 1 hour later when you
walk across this line. So if I'm
in Poland and I cross over into Lithuania, I have
to change my watch. My clock has changed.
That's kind of crazy when you think about it. Because if
I'm right next to this line right here
and I want to have dinner, this person
on this side is not ready for dinner yet. It's not dinner time
over here. I've already finished over here. They've not begun.
And it could be just 1 mile away, 1 km away.
That's kind of crazy. And it's crazy because we know time
is a spectrum. We know it's constantly traveling. But what
humans did was divide up. And the reason they
divided up time was so that we could all go to work and
we could all be slaves. And so the
train would run on time, meaning they could create a schedule that
we would then have to obey. So my point is this
is reality. This landscape is reality
and this line is invented. So now if
I put another invention down, we recognize this as a
piano keyboard. And this note and this note for
males. This is the dreaded E and F area
which everybody in all the old vocal books know to be
episage a breakpoint. And that's exactly
where Poland and Lithuania are, right there, right down
that line. And so if I'm singing,
there's this huge border right there and I have to show my
passport and I've got to go through immigration and I've got to get to
this other side here. And that's a whole lot of work. So I'm going
to avoid doing that as a beginner singer. And I'm just going to go.