Her and into a child. And then of course
through puberty and adulthood. But the connection
that we make and how we all are using our voices I
obviously was developing English along with my voice
use. You people mostly were developing Polish or
whatever language was spoken in the home. And so all
of that sort of begs to be of recognized
is the best word. Because anyone that feels
like a beginner or identifies as a beginner is
not giving themselves credit for all the years
that they've already been using their voice. And that matters when
it comes to singing and revealing oneself through a song.
And so when we think about beginners, some of you
here might also be a beginner teacher.
And that again is a funny term to be a beginner teacher
because as soon as we are able to speak and if you
have siblings or friends, you've been teaching
all throughout your life. And it's just a formal
label that we put that I use. And many
people use that. They teach math or they teach English
or they teach science. But there's
many times that we're teaching throughout our life that we don't
think of it as teaching. And so if you think back to voice use,
who was your first teacher?
Of course, everybody's. Parents or caretakers.
And did they have a degree? Did they have
any education in raising another human?
Was there lessons that they took?
No is the answer. They just nine
months previous had a really good night and then boom,
here we are. And so the idea of becoming
the most important person in the world to somebody should
have some formal training to go with it, but it
does not. And so when you think about taking on
giving advice to another person as a teacher,
you want to give advice to a singer that wants to
improve. You may feel a lot of pressure. You may feel
like, I don't know if I know enough, I don't know if I'm
educated enough in order to help somebody sing better.
But the truth is you are just by the act
of caring, by the act of wanting to help.
And so what do you think is the most important thing
that I know that beginner singers don't
know? Think about
that. What is the most important thing that I know
that beginner singers do not know?
The answer is I know they can sing.
They don't know they can sing. They don't trust themselves,
they're doubting. And so the whole reason that
they would come to me or you or anyone teaching
is that they need evidence, they need convincing.
And so your ability to help guide them
through all of their doubt is what lessons basically
take. So when you think back to parents, what did parents
teach their kids? They taught them that they knew
they could speak and so they just over a
time oh do boo boo. This is Mama
this is dada. We make sounds,
we play with our voice and this is the best way to
introduce controlled voice use to
anyone no matter their age. And how
did your parents teach you to walk? Did they teach you
about the muscles in your legs? Did they teach you
about balance and how to move your arms?
No, they simply knew you could walk
even before you could walk. And so a baby
is simply encouraged to first crawl and
then to stand up. And as the baby stands,
it gets encouragement and then people put their arms out
and the baby tries to go. And that's exactly as a baby
is trying to formulate words and starts figuring out that
these words have meaning and that it creates actions
and responses. So there's a whole lot going on
in the mind as we are learning to walk and talk and
navigate our families. And that's really important
to remember many years later. Now when you
have another person in front of you desiring
to do better, your belief that
they can is number one is so
important. And that's really important to remember because
singing is innate, just like walking is innate.
So we're not really teaching people how to sing.
Even though we describe the many muscles that are involved.
Usually we have a focus of about 20
or maybe 30 muscles tops that we start explaining
to people. These are what the vocal folds are doing and the thyroid,
arynoid muscle and many different muscles that we're familiar with. But there
are up to 100 muscles that are responsible
for me speaking right now and I'm not thinking of any of
them and neither do you when you speak.
And so it's not really how to sing that we're focused
on, it's what to sing.
Just like when our parents taught us
how to walk, they really taught us where
to walk. Walk over here, don't walk in the
street don't walk down those stairs without me.
So the idea of navigating the world was
taught by boundaries. And we want to navigate our
voice the same way. Because once we establish a song,
there's going to be boundaries, there will be a melody, there will be
lyrics. So now all of a sudden, what was free is now
in restricted form. And so it's really important to just
remember that what to sing is what we're giving
choices to people. And I like to take it a step further and
explain what to think. Because the perspective that someone
has, like they identify themselves as
a beginner, that perspective is very important that
it change so that their body is free.
Because what's happening up in here,
what's happening up in here is now going to rain down through
all those connections, all those nerves. And what
we're working ourselves through is not ignorance.
These people are not dumb to voice use,
they're simply inhibited.
And so as that perspective is trying to rain down.
If somebody is afraid to walk or afraid
of where they're walking, their motions will be very
restricted, very tense. If you're walking
next to a very high cliff or if you're walking in a bad neighborhood,
your movements will reflect that there
is danger in your mind. Just like
when people speak to somebody that they're friends with,
with somebody that they're intimate with, their voice use is
very comfortable. But in a situation like this,
when I know there's people listening, I can feel that I'm aware
of how I'm speaking. And obviously, when we sing, we are
aware that people are listening and assessing.
So it's a different circumstance. So we have to work through
that inhibition. And as teachers, we help others
work through that inhibition.
And so let me see where I am here.
So the learning to sing is really learning to get through that
inhibition. And the way to do that is to take the instrument that
everybody I get asked a lot. I don't know about you, but I get asked
a lot if I believe everyone can sing.
And yes, I believe everyone can sing,
just not well, because everybody has these parts,
because the parts of the voice and everyone who
can speak can sing. But in order
to sing with intentional sounds, in order to sing with
grace, we need to build a better instrument.
So really, learning to sing well means
learning to become a better instrument.
An instrument that's compliant agrees
with the laws of physics and an instrument that
is connected to your thoughts, to your whims.
Imagine if you went to a guitar lesson
and the first lesson you walked in without a guitar
and the teacher handed you a piece of wood and said,
here's a picture of a guitar, here's the material
that it's made out of. I want you to go home and make this
instrument and then when you come back, I will teach you how
to play it. And if that was the case,
the instrument we would build would probably be something like
this.
It would not be in agreement with the laws of sound.
It takes a long time to become a craftsman
at building an instrument. It has to agree
with the laws of physics. And so when we learn to sing,
ideally, all we're doing is learning to be in agreement with
the physics of sound and with the revealing
of our whims. And so that combination means we've
always been able to sing, but now we need to organize that
so that we are becoming a better instrument.
And so people ask me all the time what are the
most important things to be a better instrument?
And especially if I'm working with somebody that's a professional.
The first absolute number one most important thing for the condition
of your voice is sleep.
That has the most influence on what the
instrument's ability to do is because there's a
hierarchy when sleep is deprived
our focus wanes. And when sleep is deprived,
our digestion changes. It's what's called a
circadian rhythm. The body has an internal clock.
And if we don't get proper sleep, good sleep,
deep sleep, if we don't get deep sleep,
then all of the systems are thrown off the timing.
And so you may not be able to digest food.
You may have trouble with mucous membranes being dry.
And like I said, the focus is gone. And so
sleep is number one most important. But if I ask
a beginner to get more sleep, will that
improve their skills? Probably not. And so
it goes beyond that. And the next number two
most important influence on the voice,
it is hydration. And hydration
is number two, even though we all talk about it like it's number one.
Because if you are lacking sleep, if you don't
have proper sleep, then no amount of water you drink will
reach those cells because it is in deep sleep.
Deep sleep, right there. It is in deep sleep where
the cells are replenished. First they're cleansed
and then they're hydrated. And so deep sleep is the
deep clean that our voice needs. And of course,
hydration is the tool to flush out toxins, but also
to replenish. And so hydration is more than just drinking
water. It also means your trace mineral levels
and sodium levels in your body because that's
how the body retains that hydration retains
that water. And so diet is tied to
that as well as sleep. But that's number two. And so
the number three most important
influence on our voice would be vocalizing.
Vocalizing is the act of exercising the voice
and challenging it in many different ways
just exactly like we exercise our bodies.
And as we do that, we want to put focus
on where we find weaknesses and lacks
of coordination. It's kind of the opposite of
what we do when we sing songs. And so although everybody
enjoys singing songs and can't wait to get there during
a lesson, though vocalizing the warming up
the exercises present a much better way to enhance
the instrument to connect it. Because the biggest
hurdle we face when you feel like a beginner
or when you're working with somebody that identifies as a beginner
is a fear of singing. And that, of course,
doesn't really mean they fear singing. What they really fear is
the embarrassment. The embarrassment that comes
along with socially unacceptable sounds.
When they sing, they feel very vulnerable.
They feel exposed. And so
that feeling will reflect in their voice and they
will lose control, of course. And so really what we need to
encourage when we're working with somebody without much experience is
they need to sort of like boost their courage.
So I like to try and keep it very simple. When I'm working with
somebody that feels they are a beginner,
it can be very overwhelming to them. And I
applaud them for seeking help because it's
always better to work with somebody an outside opinion
in order to really assess where you may be getting in your way.
And it takes courage just to reach out to somebody. So we
have to remember as teachers that this is a big leap
of faith when somebody comes to us and says that they're a
beginner singer and want help because they're assuming there's
a lot of rules to singing and they want to make sure they get those
right. And so the first thing to encourage them to do is
to applaud themselves for having the courage to step it
up. So my word to them is we look for two
things. I just want beginners to be comfortable
and in control, and there's
two things to each. So when we talk
about comfort, there is both physical
comfort that's obvious, but there's also emotional
comfort. And those two are very different,
yet affect each other. So when working with
somebody without much experience, I like to focus on emotional
comfort. I want to make sure that what they do is
being encouraged, that there are no bad sounds.
I want them to be playful, I want to be brave
and.