Sam
sam
SA.
Sam sam
sam
SA.
Hello. Hello, everybody. Good afternoon, Mark. Good evening,
Polish people. We are very happy to start
our first of a
few that we plan to do a few
vocal trainings for singers and singing teachers. We are very
happy that you are with us here.
It's 07:00. Maybe I will ask
Mark to make a short introduction before we start recording.
And let me just prepare my second computer, because I
just ran out from work and came
home. Our vice president, Paulina Tujinska,
is not well, as she's pregnant, and today
I will host the
workshop. Dagmara, are you hosting? Also?
Great. So I just have to give you
some I can yeah.
Okay. Dagmara is also our Mixingers
association member. Let me just give you okay,
now you're a co host. Great. So let
me just prepare the second laptop, and, Mark, if you can
say a word, I will be happy. Welcome. Check, one,
two. Good to see you. Recording in progress.
Got it. Glad to be with everybody.
I'd like to keep it as casual as possible, so if
there's questions, I'm open to answering any
and all of them along the way.
And during the course of our
working together, today is going to be focused on beginners. Tomorrow will
be focused more on advanced.
But there's no bad question, and there's
no bad time to ask it.
Somebody will be monitoring the chat, is that correct?
Yes, I will be the one today.
Okay, so I'll ask you then, because I don't want to be looking at
the chat while I'm talking.
I'll ask you at any time, so you can feel free to fire away at
any point, and then she'll collect them and ask at appropriate
times. Do you wish
to me to collect them? And if you say there will
be time for questions, and you don't want to be interrupted
by questions that are yeah, I think it's best I'll
ask, are there any questions? And then you can let me know.
Yeah. Okay. Let me just start the second recording.
The more we do, the better,
the safer we are.
Just a second.
I just have to come into the zoom as I
have a second zoom on myself. And this is the association zoom.
So I have to re log in. It will take a minute,
and I need you to allow me to share my screen.
Right. Dagmara, can you do it now?
I cannot hear you. Yes, I'm all right. Trying to do this.
So should I just make Mark a co host?
Yeah, it's possible. Or you can just allow him to share his screen.
I don't know what is better.
It okay. Got it. I'll start with I'm not sure if I
can, actually, because I'm just being a co host, not a
host. Okay, I will do
it.
I have to allow myself to record from the second laptop.
I can also share for
everyone. Too much to do.
I just didn't know that I will be the host today because okay,
recording done. We can start. Yeah. And so allow
you to share your screen, please.
Let's do it this way. Everybody can share the screen now.
I hope that only Mark will do it.
Does it work so far? Yep. I'm just going to get my slides
and then we'll find out. I hope so.
Doom beginners.
Let's see,
before we start, just a word you can see
downstairs, the participants. You can see the
writing, the button pokash NAPIS.
Okre, napisi. Show the subtitles
or don't show. So you can click show the
subtitles and you will see what's been
told. So there is automatic transcription
from English to English because maybe some words
that you will not be sure if you understand, it will be easier to
watch them written. So it works this way.
Dominique, will you be translating as I speak?
No, I just said that there
will be only the automatic transcription. So whatever you
say, there is a boat
that writes it down so they
can see the English written transcription. But we don't
translate those trainings with you because it
would take double time to get the knowledge. And many people
in Poland already speak English well enough to understand
what you say. Okay, well, I added my bad
version of Polish on my slide, so hopefully
I'm not embarrassing myself too much.
We are always impressed that you prepare so well for all
those lectures and you use our language,
which is a really surprise for us. Well, I abuse your
language. That's what I do. Anyway, thank you
for preparation.
The first thing that I'll start off with is just simply that
word beginner. Because if anybody is identifying
as a beginner, we have to think about this
for a second, because we're talking about voice use,
and there really is no adult beginner
when it comes to voice use, because we've all
been using our voice since this since day
one. And so these are the true beginners right here.
And when you think about all of the exploration
that we do when we are first born with our voice,
when you think about all of the experimentation that
goes on, the size and shape of the larynx,
even the vocal folds themselves are very different for an infant.
And there are little stylite cells and the
edges of the vocal folds, the fold itself is not multilayered
for an infant. It is a monolayered, meaning there's just
one layer and it's waiting for use in order to
trigger this incredible evolution through toddlers.