Used muscle tension to resolve lots of problems,
immediate problems of just hitting a note, getting the volume I needed or
the sound I needed. And in doing so, I really created
a very external way of singing that cost me,
obviously, my longevity. And so
I would start losing my voice by the end of the night. Then I
had another problem. So all of this gets very complex.
So I had to break it down to survival.
And as I started to study the voice, it became apparent that
what they were talking about in theory of isolating
a pitch, I could never practice that in reality because
when I'm singing a chorus of a song, it also has a timbre
and it also has a volume. So it was never applying. So I
at first took melodies from songs and made them into exercises
with the first students I was working with. And I
wasn't good enough at it because they kept recognizing the songs
I was using. So they just wanted to sing that song. And I was like,
all right, this is not working. So what I found to be useful about exercises
is that no one has sung it before.
So I will create a melody that person in
front of me hasn't sung. Therefore they have no reference.
And so if it is an unfamiliar melody,
now we can start with a blank canvas and now start
to talk about the attributes. What is the volume? Did you just
get louder or softer along with changing pitch?
And the more I ask those questions, the more they are developing a
very good perception, a very larger perception of the whole
of the voice, not just one aspect or another.
And so I have a lot of exercises that I use
simply because I think of a variety. Just like
when you go to the gym, I think they call it muscle confusion
when you constantly change the exercise.
And the reason for that is that brains are very good at finding
shortcuts. So if you use the same exercise or
the same melody, the brain will find a shortcut of
where the end result you want is. And that loses value
as an exercise. So I will change something
about the melody or the volume or the timbre just
to keep the brain processing so that they can
develop beggars skills and not just have single programs
that they follow.
There's a question. Can I ask a question? So when you
teach somebody and you're talking about pitch, you have
four things. Do you give a mention to the others? In other words,
do this pitch. I want you to stay at the same volume. Is there always
a nod to each one of those individual focuses so that people
are conscious of each one and they've got a direction
on each one at the same time? Yes, absolutely.
Because when somebody will come to me, especially a hyper functioning
singer will say, listen to my voice.
That pitch, that pitch right there doesn't work.
I'm encountering this a lot where somebody will sing up a scale and
they'll have a particular pitch and I'll say,
okay, sounds like a broken string on a guitar or a piano
that doesn't work. And obviously we know that's not true,
but they're imagining this as a scale.
Hear that? And so I will say,
okay, let's take that and do this
now. So with a different
timbre, all of a sudden they will get a success.
Or if they lower the volume or raise the volume, the same pitch
that they said didn't work does work. So they begin
to see that it's a circumstance, not a pitch.
And the circumstance involves all four things.
Obviously time somebody
will be able to sustain for a little bit and then the voice goes
in the trash. That's one issue. Or they
will start in a trash and then come out of it using more force,
of course. So all of these circumstances are always,
those four things are always affecting each other. So for
therapy's sake, the obvious funny answer is, okay,
if that note doesn't work, don't sing it. Sing it louder,
sing it softer, sing it with a different timbre. And I
know everybody here does that as well, of just asking that sound
to share a different space. So we'll go a little darker,
a little brighter, a little deeper, a little bit louder, a little
bit softer. It's a joystick and it's a four
dimension sphere. That's why I like the ball as
an analogy. Because there is no top or bottom, there is
no left or right. It is a sphere. And so therefore,
we could start at any point on a sphere and
include the whole rest of its volume.
And so to answer your question, yes, I always mention
the volume that we're at and the timbre that
we're using and the duration that we're holding it.
And I find duration to be the sticking point as people
will continually hold a note until they like the sound.
That's a cheat. That can't happen in a song. And so
I find those singers that tend to hold a note until they like it,
they get overwhelmed when singing a song because the tempo
is clicking by and they want some notes back that they didn't like how
they came out. But now the tempo of the song keeps
them moving. And so I will have somebody
sing something again.
Voice cracks or something, I'll say, okay, don't stall on that
note. I don't want
them to do that because that's going to form a belief in their mind that
they can always fix something on the fly. When it's
more like throwing a ball, you don't get the ball back once
it leaves your hand. So if it misses its target, you could
throw again. But you can't change the trajectory
of the ball once it's released. And that's exactly what we're doing.
When we're releasing sound waves, they already have a trajectory
and a response. The listener has already heard it. And so getting
in real time, getting present, is all a part of this development
of being a better instrument, one that responds in
real time, in four dimensions. As you have a thought,
it's occurring here. It's very scary to people in
the beginning that their thoughts are going to translate into
sounds immediately, but that's singing,
and that's why we feel vulnerable. But that's why it's
so powerful. When done well, it is the sound
of the truth. And as we reveal ourselves in
a song, if we have that flow, that's empathy
that everybody on the planet can feel, can understand, they can
hear inhibition, they can hear hesitation. And so when that's missing,
the sound of our voice is the sound of a truth.
Even if we're not feeling what we're singing about at that moment,
that's what the skill is all about, to recreate the human
experience on command. So building
this instrument for developing singers,
which is the term I like to use instead of beginner, is that they're developing
an instrument. I like to make sure we stay on all
four of those parameters all the time. So if they're
new to it and have never explored their voice very simple exercises,
very playful. And the more advanced somebody is in their development,
the more we talk about the nuance and the real small detail,
a subtle change in volume, a subtle change in
timbre, and it just depends on what challenge
a person is up for.
Great. I cannot see any more exercises
as there is already 1
hour talk. Actually, we have one. Marcia Book
would like to also now
you need to unmute Marcia.
Sorry. I actually think I actually already asked the question,
so you can just drop your hand or maybe I will lower
your okay, great.
So we have two more hours and six singers.
So do we have Alex ready? I cannot
see him. Alex, can you raise your hand?
Yeah, I can see him now.
Alex? Hello.
Can you turn your video on?
Yes.
I'll just add you to the spotlight with Mark.
Where are you? I couldn't see. I'm here.
Say something again. Now I can see. Okay. Hello.
Got it? Yeah. And where is
Alex?
My problem is voice is
no blading registers.
And so does your mother or father have a very deep voice?
My father. And do you sound like your father?
No. Does he have a lower voice than you?
I don't know. Oh, you know.
Have you seen your father?
No. Oh, okay. And so
who in the household where you live has a deep voice?
Somebody else? Yeah.
And so if I ask you to make that sound,
what happens?
So here's the deal, Alex. When you're at A,
what's your favorite sport?
Running. Running, you said?
Yeah. If you're watching a good friend win
a race and you're in the stands watching,
are you going to go, yeah, that's good, I'm glad, or are
you going to go, whoa, yeah.
Which reaction would be more normal once?
So can you your best friend just won
a race and you go, whoa, can I hear that
sound? You make that sound or your version of it doesn't have to be what
I did.
One person. Okay, so Alex,
we can see this very clearly
that this is not a vocal issue, this is an
Alex issue. And so I
was you when I was 16, that's how old you are, right?
16, yeah. When I was 16, I was exactly
like you in that I did not want to do anything stupid
or anything that would cause me to be embarrassed.
And so I spoke down here, and I spoke
down here a lot, and I was just going through puberty,
obviously, and so therefore there was a lot of confusion.
My skin was terrible, I was very skinny, and I
was afraid of the universe.
And so the idea of making
big joyous sounds was like out of the question.
Let's interrupt you two questions. Alex or Axel?
Because I had to axel, sorry. So you're Axel,
not Alex. Somebody wrote me down
the bad version. Okay, the second question, axel,
do you need any translation?
Had a better understanding. Thank you.
Mark movie barzoniski.
I just translated that when you've been
growing up, you also tries to
speak with your low voice. And so it is
so five years ago,
when you were eleven years old, if you had a kitty in
your hands, a kitten, you would say, kitty,
kitty, kitty, kitty Kim.
So I want you to pet the kitty and go,
excellent, that's great. Now do the same thing.
Yes, to us.
Awesome, great. So now
I want you to go, he stuck.
He no,
that's okay. So do this,
Axel, do this.
But I want more noise right in that middle where it's he
I want e namituza.
But and
so Axel, do you know right where that spot is
where your voice breaks?
No. Can we do this?
Can.