A. Make that sound
good.
Yeah.
You? Yeah.
Good. Yeah.
Good.
Yeah.
Beginning good.
So, Axel, would you say your low note is
lower volume than the high note or louder
volume?
Can you ask him if he thinks the low note is louder
or softer than where he begins?
Repeat please. Because I was on the chat with
our participants, so I'm looking to see
if he thinks that the low note is louder
or softer than where he's beginning.
The softer low note is softer. I agree.
And so can he please pay attention?
OOH.
Keep it loud.
Shimito guash. No.
Repeat please. Mark, I'm sorry, because people are asking me questions
on pref, on chat about the organization's things.
I have to do everything at once. Repeat,
please. They don't pay you enough.
And so I'm just asking for the volume to stay
the same as he descends, for his focus to be on that
that it stays loud.
Yaksarashi Machid.
Nolitonadora.
Who.
Did I lose them?
Wow. I'm afraid we did.
Okay,
maybe let's just no, we have Alex Axel, our user.
Yeah, we'll just okay,
we're back.
So now the other way.
This way. Constrona.
But you
want the noise.
Olaras slower.
Pavoli grasna will translate and I will us answer
the questions on each other.
The goal here is Axel's
brain is avoiding what is uncomfortable
both physically and emotionally. So there is the gap,
of course, the muscles,
right. Big gap between them. And so what I'm
asking him to do by going slowly is to discover all
of this uncoordinated stuff in the middle. We are trained
to avoid that because of embarrassment.
And so sitting right there, where the awkward
spot is Oakness
of the vocal folds, by delaying that,
trying to desensitize the avoidance,
it is unconscious. He's not thinking to avoid it,
he wants to sing there. But it is unconsciously being
avoided because brains hate embarrassment. And so
those are the two working zones that's Poland
and Lithuania. And so we got nothing in the shared space
here. And so I want him to go very slowly through that area,
and I would ideally ask somebody to go right there
immediately.
Axel, can you make that sound?
Axel. Taki sam jivings. Probably.
Ah.
Hello. Axel. Putrabiya.
Hello. Hello. Is the stamrugim
okay?
It good.
A little higher.
Ah. Too clear.
We want noisy.
WA.
Still too good. We want worse.
Wow.
Zawadmi. We want ugly.
Almost. Wow.
Ah. As like a witch. Yeah,
my little pretty.
Yeah. Lower volume. Yeah.
OOH. OOH.
OOH.
OOH. So the
volume disappeared.
We need the volume to be the same.
OOH.
It's la.
La. La.
Good. La.
La.
Volume. La.
Same volume. La.
But we want the noise. La.
We want noisy. Ah.
Too clean. Too good. We want noisy.
La.
So la.
Start in the noise. La.
La. La.
Yes, yes. La.
Eight notes. This many notes. La.
La. So la.
La. One note.
La. No,
keep going. Even if it sounds bad. Keep going,
La.
More notes with noise will give you
halfway to La.
Connecting La.
We want noise in between.
La. La.
La. That's okay. Now from
there,
laxel axel.
La.
La. Good. So now pitch
has dropped La.
So we need this la.
It's going to be an ugly ending. That's okay.
La make
this sound.
Ah.
That's not the pitch.
Plus noise. So now
great.
OOH.
Sing.
Yes. See?
OOH.
O. Yes. See OOH.
WA. Okay,
we gotta finish.
O.
Yes.
Slower. O.